Guide to the Carol Gelderman Papers, 1981-1984
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The Carol Gelderman Papers
1981-1984
Gelderman, Carol W.
4.9 cubic feet (7 Boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
This collection comprises the research material Carol Gelderman compiled for use in her biography of Mary McCarthy, entitled Mary McCarthy: A Life. The bulk of the collection is interview material, including audio cassettes. Several of the interviews were with Mary McCarthy but most were with others who knew or worked with McCarthy. There is also correspondence as well as articles and portions of books either by or about Mary McCarthy and her work.
Biographical Note
Carol Wettlaufer Gelderman, born on 2 December 1939, first became interested in Mary McCarthy after discovering they had both been educated for a time by The Religious of the Sacred Heart. This interest of hers would eventually lead to writing or editing several pieces about Mary McCarthy, including Mary McCarthy: A Life, the first comprehensive biography of Mary McCarthy, and Conversations with Mary McCarthy. She also contributed to Twenty-four Ways of Looking at Mary McCarthy: The Writer and Her Work.
Scope and Content Note
This collection comprises the research material Carol Gelderman compiled for use in her biography of Mary McCarthy, entitled Mary McCarthy: A Life. The bulk of the collection is interview material, including audio cassettes. Several of the interviews were with Mary McCarthy but most were with others who knew or worked with McCarthy. There is also correspondence as well as articles and portions of books either by or about Mary McCarthy and her work.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Mary McCarthy Papers
Subject Headings
Names:
McCarthy, Mary, 1912-1989; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972
Subjects:
Novelists; Women authors--Biography
Places:
Castine (Me.)
Document Types:
Interviews; Photographs
VCL Categories
Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Madeleine Amodio, July 2011.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the collection was received in 2005 from Carol Gelderman (M2005-016). Additional material was received in 2009 (M2009-014).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
A tape player is required to play the tapes in Series X.
Series List
- Series I. Forebears
  Series I contains original photographs given to Carol Gelderman by Mary McCarthy which portray her family and herself, and also a detailed file on Simon Manly Preston, Mary McCarthy's great-grandfather.
- Series II. Early Childhood
  Series II contains notes, correspondence, and research conducted by Carol Gelderman into Mary McCarthy's early Seattle childhood.
- Series III. Vassar Years
  Series III contains copies of prose composed by Mary McCarthy in her time at Vassar College, as well as reviews of The Group and interviews and articles about Mary McCarthy and her time at Vassar.
- Series IV. First Marriage
  Series IV contains both interviews and articles published during the time of Mary McCarthy's first marriage and correspondence from Mary McCarthy to Emmanuel Roussuck, who was an art dealer who routinely lent her paintings for parties.
- Series V. Partisan Review
  Series V contains articles and interviews taken from the Partisan Review. The bulk of this series is interviews with friends of Mary McCarthy.
- Series VI. Second Marriage
  Series VI contains information pertaining to Mary McCarthy's second marriage, including personal information about Edmund Wilson and articles both by and about Mary McCarthy published during the time of her second marriage.
- Series VII. Third Marriage/Later Years
  Series VII contains research and information about Mary McCarthy in her later years, and during the time period of her third marriage.
- Series VIII. Fourth Marriage
  Series VIII contains, along with information about the CIA's investigation into Mary McCarthy, information about her from the time period of her fourth marriage, including information about her Vietnam trip and the Lillian Hellman/Mary McCarthy court case.
- Series IX. Interview Transcriptions and Interview Requests
  Series IX contains interview requests and written interviews conducted by Carol Gelderman.
- Series X. Recorded Interviews
  Series X contains cassette tape recordings of interviews Carol Gelderman conducted with various people. The numbering system for this series was devised by the archivist.
- Series XI. Mary McCarthy Correspondence
  Series XI contains correspondence from and to Mary McCarthy, with the bulk being copies of letters Mary McCarthy sent to others.
- Series XII. Miscellaneous
  Series XII contains various correspondence and reviews of Mary McCarthy: A life, as well as several publications pertaining to Gelderman's research.
Container List
- Series I: Forebears
  - Original Mary McCarthy Photos (Folder 1.1)
  - Simon Manly Preston (Folder 1.2)
- Series II: Early Childhood
  - Early Childhood (Folder 1.3)
  - Seattle Years- Forest Ridge 1912-1918 (Folder 1.4)
  - Seattle Years- Annie Wright Episcopal 1912-1918 (Folder 1.5)
- Series III: Vassar Years
  - Vassar College (Folders 1.6-1.7)
  - Vassar Years- Interviews/Articles (Folder 1.8)
- Series IV: First Marriage
  - First Marriage- Interviews/Articles (Folder 1.9)
  - Emmanuel Roussuck - Art Dealer (Folder 1.10)
- Series V: Partisan Review
  - Articles/Miscellaneous (Folders 1.11-1.12)
  - Interviews (Folder 1.13)
  - Interviews- Irving Howe (Folder 7.1)
  - Interviews- Dwight Macdonald to Nicola Chiaromonte (Folder 7.2)
  - Interviews- Dwight Macdonald (Folder 1.14)
  - Interviews- Delmore Schwartz (Folder 1.15)
  - Interviews- Stephen Spender (Folder 1.16)
- Series VI: Second Marriage
  - Personal Information/Edmund Wilson (Folder 1.17)
  - Second Marriage- Edmund Wilson Information- Rosalind Wilson (Folder 1.18)
  - Portsmouth/Wellfleet- The Oasis Xerox- Robert Cowell Papers, 1949-1955 (Folder 1.19)
  - Part VI: Jim West, 1960-1987 (Folder 1.20)
  - Second Marriage- Articles By/About Mary McCarthy- Articles, 1940-1945 (Folder 1.21)
- Series VII: Third Marriage/Later Years
  - Hannah Arendt From 1949 (Folder 1.22)
  - Hannah Arendt From 1949- Reviews of Hannah Arendt (Folder 1.23)
  - Articles/Books about Mary McCarthy, 1949-1962 (Folder 1.24)
  - Articles/Books about Mary McCarthy, 1949-1962 (Folder 7.3)
  - Articles About Mary McCarthy, 1949-1962 (Folder 1.25)
  - The Oasis- A Xerox of 1st Edition: Random House (Folder 1.26)
  - Later Years- Carol Gelderman Interviews with Mary McCarthy (Folder 2.1)
  - Later Years- Carol Gelderman Interviews with Mary McCarthy- Summer 1984 (Folder 2.2)
  - Carol Gelderman Stuff- Letters from Library, etc.- 3rd/4th Marriage, Later Years (Folder 2.3)
  - Third Marriage- Articles by Mary McCarthy (Folder 2.6)
  - Third Marriage- Articles by Mary McCarthy- Congress for Cultural Freedom (Folder 2.7)
  - Third Marriage- Articles by Mary McCarthy- John Davenport (Folder 2.8)
- Series VIII: Fourth Marriage
  - Investigation by CIA into Mary McCarthy (Folder 2.4)
  - Vietnam- Vietnam (Folder 2.9)
  - Vietnam- Articles about Mary McCarthy/Vietnam (Folder 2.10)
  - Writings- Later Life- Mary McCarthy Speeches (Folder 2.11)
  - Writings- Later Life-Articles/Book Reviews by Mary McCarthy (Folder 2.12)
  - Writings- Later Life-Articles/Book Reviews about Mary McCarthy, 1963-1987 (Folder 2.13)
  - Writings- Later Life (Folders 2.14-2.15)
  - Writings- Later Life (Folder 7.4)
  - Lillian Hellman/Mary McCarthy- Articles about Lillian Hellman and Mary McCarthy (Folder 2.16)
  - Lillian Hellman/Mary McCarthy- Mary McCarthy/Lillian Hellman Court Case (Folder 2.17)
  - Articles/Book Reviews- Mary McCarthy Bibliography (Folder 2.18)
  - Articles/Book Reviews- Inventory of Mary McCarthy Archives at Vassar (Folder 2.19)
  - Articles/Book Reviews- Mary McCarthy Death Notices (Folder 2.20)
- Series IX: Interviews and Interview Requests
  - Malcolm Cowley, Sherman, Ct. (Folder 2.30)
  - Mrs Alan Barth (Folder 2.31)
  - Mrs Elizabeth (Jerome) Greenebaum (Folder 2.32)
  - Judy Knickerbocker- Mrs Nicholas (Folder 2.33)
  - Helen Wilson (Folder 2.34)
  - Helen Sawyer Farnsworth - Mrs Jerry (Folder 2.35)
  - Mrs Robert Penn Warren (Folder 2.36)
  - Dr Gordon Ray, President of the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Folder 2.37)
  - Possible Talk Stuff (Folder 3.1)
  - William Buell Radio Free Europe (Folder 3.2)
  - OECD Francis Cassavetti (Folder 3.3)
  - Dick Cavett- Channel 13 (Folder 3.4)
  - Mrs F.W. Dupec (Folder 3.5)
  - Mr and Mrs David DuVivier (Folder 3.6)
  - Mrs Nicola Chiaromonte (Folder 3.7)
  - Mrs Thomas Finletter- Eileen Geist (Folder 3.8)
  - Philippe Franchine (Folder 3.9)
  - Mrs Stuart Frazier (Folder 3.10)
  - Stanley Geist (Folder 3.11)
  - Brendan Gill - The New Yorker (Folder 3.12)
  - Alan Gilyn (Folder 3.13)
  - Hester Green and Mark Hamilton of A.M. Heath (Folder 3.14)
  - Doris Grumbach (Folder 3.15)
  - Walter Goldwater (Folder 3.16)
  - Clement Greenberg (Folder 3.17)
  - Miriam Gross (Folder 3.18)
  - Elizabeth Hardwick (Folder 3.19)
  - Francis Haskell (Folder 3.20)
  - Mrs Benjamin Hibshman (Folder 3.21)
  - Mary Hooven (Folder 3.22)
  - Kot Jelenski (Folder 3.23)
  - Mrs John Jessup- Eunice Clark (Folder 3.24)
  - Colton Johnson Telephone Interview (Folder 3.25)
  - Gloria Jones - Mrs James (Folder 3.26)
  - William Jovanovich (Folder 3.27)
  - Ward Just (Folder 3.28)
  - Harold Kavlan (Folder 3.29)
  - Mr and Mrs Terence Kilmartin (literary editor of Observer) (Folder 3.30)
  - Nicholas King (Folder 3.31)
  - Dr Lotte Kohler (Folder 3.32)
  - Lady Caroline Lowell (Folder 3.33)
  - Mme Angelique Levi (Folder 3.34)
  - Mary McCarthy to Mrs Robert Lowell- Elizabeth Hardwick (Folder 3.35)
  - Dwight Macdonald (Folder 3.36)
  - Nancy Macdonald (Folder 3.37)
  - Flip McCarthy (Folder 3.38)
  - Mary Dabney McCarthy San Francisco (Folder 3.39)
  - Kevin McCarthy (Folder 3.40)
  - Kevin McCarthy- Mary McCarthy Interviews Done for People (Folder 3.41)
  - Preston McCarthy (Folder 3.42)
  - Mrs Sheridan McCarthy (Folder 3.43)
  - James Merrill (Folder 3.44)
  - Professor Ulrich Middledorf (Folder 3.45)
  - Karl Miller (Folder 3.46)
  - Herbert Mitgang (Folder 3.47)
  - Mr and Mrs William Mostyn-Owen (Folder 3.48)
  - Mrs Curt Muser (Folder 3.49)
  - John Myers (Folder 3.50)
  - Ellen Adler Oppenheim (Folder 3.51)
  - Interview with Ben O'Sullivan (Folder 3.52)
  - Benjamin O'Sullivan Interview (Folder 3.53)
  - Cees Nooteboom (Folder 3.54)
  - Cleo Paturis (Folder 3.55)
  - Eleanor Perenai (Folder 3.56)
  - William Phillips (Folder 3.57)
  - Mrs William Prince- Augusta Dabney (Folder 3.58)
  - Jonathan Kaudal - International Herald Tribune (Folder 3.59)
  - John Richardson (Folder 3.60)
  - Yale Richmond (Folder 3.61)
  - Jess Rosenberg (Folder 3.62)
  - Larry Rivers (Folder 3.63)
  - Mrs John Russell- Peggy Besnier (Folder 3.64)
  - Mayer Schapiro (Folder 3.65)
  - Brandt and Brandt (Folder 3.66)
  - Arthur Schelsinger, Jr (Folder 3.67)
  - The Reverend Mr and Mrs F.Q. Shafer (Folder 3.68)
  - Elizabeth Niebuhr Sifton (Folder 3.69)
  - William Shawn (Folder 3.70)
  - Robert Silvers (Folder 3.71)
  - Eileen Simpson (Folder 3.72)
  - Roger Straws (Folder 3.73)
  - Werner Stemans (Folder 3.74)
  - Eve Stwertka (Folder 3.75)
  - Signora Fiorella Superbi (Folder 3.76)
  - Diana Trilling (Folder 3.77)
  - Niccolo Tucci (Folder 3.78)
  - Frank Preston (Folder 3.79)
  - William Tuohy- LA Times (Folder 3.80)
  - Margo Viscusi (Folder 3.81)
  - Nick Wahl (Folder 3.82)
  - Mrs Charles Walker (Folder 3.83)
  - Lord George Weidenfeld (Folder 3.84)
  - Alison West (Folder 3.85)
  - Mrs Harold Williams (Folder 3.86)
  - Celia Woyawoda (Folder 3.87)
  - Revel Wilson (Folder 3.88)
  - Francis Wyndham (Folder 3.89)
  - Barry Zorthian (Folder 3.90)
  - Lionel Abel (Folder 4.24)
  - James Atlas (Folder 4.25)
  - R.W. Abble, Jr- NYT London International Press Center (Folder 4.26)
  - William Barrett (Folder 4.27)
  - Signora Luigi Biso (Folder 4.28)
  - Mrs William Blane (Folder 4.29)
  - Dr Seymour Bonwit (Folder 4.30)
  - Mary Brady- Mrs Leslie (Folder 4.31)
  - Thomas F.S. Buckley (Folder 4.32)
  - Irma Brandeis (Folder 4.33)
  - Bowden Broadwater (Folder 4.34)
  - [Correspondence to/from Carol Gelderman] (Folder 4.35)
- Series X: Recorded Interviews
  - Nancy Macdonald, 5 Jan 1982 (Tape 5.1)
  - Dwight Macdonald (Tape 5.2)
  - Walker- NYC, 20 Oct (Tape 5.3)
  - Elizabeth Hardwick- Her Apartment, 21 Oct 1981 (Tape 5.4)
  - Eileen Simpson Side 2 (Tape 5.5)
  - Eileen Simpson Side 1 (Tape 5.6)
  - Rosamond Russell (Tape 5.6)
  - Rosamond and John Russell (Tape 5.7)
  - Brendan Gill (Tape 5.8)
  - Shafer Side 1 (Tape 5.8)
  - Shafer Sides 2 and 3 (Tape 5.9)
  - Kevin McCarthy (Tape 5.10)
  - Kevin Sides 3 and 4 (Tape 5.11)
  - Mrs Sheridan McCarthy (Tape 5.12)
  - Preston McCarthy (Tape 5.13)
  - Mary McCarthy Interview (Tape 5.14)
  - Tom Buckley McCarthy, 12 Oct 1981 (Tape 5.15)
  - Silvers (Tape 5.16)
  - Clement Greenberg, Jan 1982 (Tape 5.17)
  - William Shawn at the New Yorker, 26 Oct 1981 (Tape 5.18)
  - Muser Side 1, 26 Oct 1981 (Tape 5.18)
  - Muser Side 2 (Tape 5.19)
  - Prof. Ulrich Middeldorf, 3 May (Tape 5.20)
  - Signora E. Sartori, 3 May (Tape 5.20)
  - Jessup (Tape 5.21)
  - Viscusi (Tape 5.22)
  - Viscusi, Jan 1982 (Tape 5.23)
  - Mrs Stuart Frazier (Tape 5.24)
  - Rosenberg Sides 1 and 2 (Tape 5.25)
  - Rosenberg Side 3 (Tape 6.1)
  - Frank Preston Side 1 (Tape 6.1)
  - Frank Preston Sides 2 and 3 (Tape 6.2)
  - Myrtle and Frank Preston Side 4, 22 March 1982 (Tape 6.3)
  - Mrs Harold Williams Side One (Tape 6.4)
  - Mrs Harold Williams Side 2, 22 March 1982 (Tape 6.3)
  - Mary Dabney McCarthy (Tape 6.4)
  - August Dabney (Tape 6.5)
  - Sir Harold Acton, 2 May (Tape 6.6)
  - Jon Nanday (Tape 6.7)
  - Randal -Washington Post Office in Paris (Tape 6.7)
  - Alison West- Institute of Fine Arts- NYU, 10 June 1982 (Tape 6.8)
  - Caroline Blackwood Lowell, 13 April 1982 (Tape 6.9)
  - Cees Nooteboom, 20 April 1982 (Tape 6.10)
  - Cees Nooteboom (Tape 6.11)
  - Cleo Paturis (Tape 6.12)
  - Francis Cassavetti, 8 Dec, 23 April 1982 (Tape 6.13)
  - William Tuohy- London, 14 April 1982 (Tape 6.14)
  - Philippe Franchine- Owner of Continental Palace in Saigon (Tape 6.15)
  - Terrence Kilmartin, 17 April 1982 (Tape 6.16)
  - Terrence Kilmartin- London, 18 April 1982 (Tape 6.17)
  - Francis Haskell- Oxford, 18 April 1982 (Tape 6.17)
  - Miriam Grass at The London Observer, 18 April 1982 (Tape 6.18)
  - Mary Brady Side 1 (Tape 6.19)
  - Doris Grumbach (Tape 6.19)
  - Countess Anna Maria Cigonga (Tape 6.20)
  - Stwertka (Tape 6.21)
  - Eve Stwertka, 9 Jan 1982 (Tape 6.22)
  - Madame Levi Sides 1 and 2 (Tape 6.23)
  - Angelique Levi (Tape 6.24)
  - Walter Goldwater (Tape 6.25)
  - Karl Miller- Head of Engineering Department University College London and London RB, 15 April 1982 (Tape 6.26)
  - Lord Weidenfeld 5-6pm, 15 April 1982 (Tape 6.26)
  - Kohler (Tape 6.27)
  - William Mostyn-Owen (Tape 6.28)
  - Gaia Servadio Mostyn-Owen, 19 April 1982 (Tape 6.29)
- Series XI: Mary McCarthy Correspondence
  - Mary McCarthy to Carmen (Folder 4.1)
  - Mary McCarthy to Jim West/Jim West to Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.2)
  - Edmund Wilson to Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.3)
  - Mary McCarthy to Edmund Wilson (Folder 4.4)
  - Mary McCarthy to Ben O'Sullivan (Folder 4.5)
  - To Frani Blough from Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.6)
  - Mary McCarthy to William Jovanovich (Folder 4.7)
  - William Jovanovich to Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.8)
  - Sales Figures (Folder 4.9)
  - Mary McCarthy to Doris Gumbach (Folder 4.10)
  - Doris Gumbach to Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.11)
  - Mary McCarthy to Bill shawn (Folder 4.12)
  - Mary McCarthy to Fred Dupeel (Folder 4.13)
  - Mary McCarhty to David and Ellie DuVivier (Folder 4.14)
  - Mary McCarthy to Bernard Berenson (Folder 4.15)
  - Mary McCarthy to Reuel Wilson/ RW to MM (Folder 4.16)
  - Mary McCarthy to Dwight MacDonald (Folder 4.17)
  - Mary McCarthy to Nicola Chiaromonte/ NC to Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.18)
  - Hannah Arendt to Mary McCarthy (Folder 4.19)
  - Mary McCarthy to Hannah Arendt (Folder 4.20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Folders 4.21-4.23)
  - Mary McCarthy to Kevin McCarthy (Folder 7.5)
- Series XII: Miscellaneous
  - Letters to Carol Gelderman from Various People (Folder 2.5)
  - Correspondence between Carol Gelderman and Mary McCarthy- Interview in Paris (Folder 2.21)
  - Correspondence between Carol Gelderman and Mary McCarthy- From Carol Gelderman to Mary McCarthy (Folder 2.22)
  - McCarthy's Corrections on Galleys (Folder 2.23)
  - [Correspondence from Mary McCarthy to Carol Gelderman] (Folder 2.24)
  - Copies of Letters between Mary McCarthy to Carol Gelderman- Some Maybe Missing i.e. in Other Files in Another Tape (Folder 2.25)
  - Mary McCarthy: A Life - Reviews- Originals (Folders 2.26-2.27)
  - Reviews of Mary McCarthy: a Life (Folder 2.28)
  - Carol Gelderman Reviews- Mary McCarthy: A Life Xerox copies (Folder 2.29)
  - Nooteboom, Cees. "Nederlandse Poëzie." Avenue. May 1982: 132-133. Print. [Dutch] (Folder 4.36)
  - Banks, William Nathaniel. "Castine, Maine, and St. Andrews, New Brunswick, Canada." The Magazine Antiques. July 1980: 102-119. Print. (Folder 4.37)